<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[derek hubbard]]></title>
  <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/feed" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-24T11:35:58-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Derek Hubbard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visual Studio 2012 Application Lifecycle Management Virtual Machine & Labs with VirtualBox]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2012/11/02/visual-studio-2012-application-lifecycle-management-virtual-machine-labs-with-virtualbox/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2012/11/02/visual-studio-2012-application-lifecycle-management-virtual-machine-labs-with-virtualbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are interested in learning and playing around with the new features in Visual Studio 2012 and Team Foundation Server 2012, but do not have access to a TFS 2012 environment yet (or maybe you get slapped on the wrist every time you try to install something new on your work machine), then the <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/briankel/archive/2011/09/16/visual-studio-11-application-lifecycle-management-virtual-machine-and-hands-on-labs-demo-scripts.aspx">Visual Studio 2012 Application Lifecycle Management (ALM) Virtual Machine</a> is for you.&nbsp; </p> <p>The ALM demo virtual machine includes both Visual Studio 2012 and Team Foundation Server 2012, plus you also get 20 hands on labs that walk you through all of the new features. The demo virtual machine is only good for a trial period of 180 days, but you can most likely expect a refreshed version of the virtual machine from Microsoft before then.&nbsp; </p> <h3>VirtualBox Support</h3> <p>The demo virtual machine will also work with VirtualBox, even though the blog post and release notes state the machine is built for Hyper-V.&nbsp; </p> <p>To run the virtual machine with VirtualBox, download and expand the self-extracting RAR files first, following the instructions provided in Brian Keller’s blog post.&nbsp; </p> <p>After extracting, you now need to create a new virtual machine using VirtualBox.&nbsp; When creating the new virtual machine, specify Windows 2008 (64-bit) for the VM operating system.&nbsp; </p> <p><a href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML562929a.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-right-width: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-left-width: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="SNAGHTML562929a" border="0" alt="SNAGHTML562929a" src="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML562929a_thumb.png" width="553" height="361"></a></p> <p>Specify an appropriate amount of memory for your new virtual machine on the next screen.&nbsp; The amount of memory you designate for your virtual machine may vary on the hardware in your machine.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </p> <p><a href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML56ea38b.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-right-width: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-left-width: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="SNAGHTML56ea38b" border="0" alt="SNAGHTML56ea38b" src="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML56ea38b_thumb.png" width="551" height="360"></a></p> <p>For the Virtual Hard Disk, specify “Use existing hard disk” and locate the vhd that was contained in the folder structure generated by the self-extracting RAR files.&nbsp; </p> <p><a href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML563d718.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-right-width: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-left-width: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="SNAGHTML563d718" border="0" alt="SNAGHTML563d718" src="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML563d718_thumb.png" width="558" height="364"></a></p> <p>You’re almost done – click Create!</p> <p>After creating, you will need to make sure you do one last step.&nbsp; Hyper-V will only build a bootable IDE hard disk, so you will need to change the settings of your new virtual machine to attach the hard disk as a bootable IDE, instead of SATA, which is the default.&nbsp; Just delete the existing hard disk, which was by default attached via the SATA controller, and add a new hard disk using the IDE controller, again pointing to the vhd which you extracted earlier.&nbsp; </p> <p>Thanks to Olof Szymczak for explaining <a href="http://ollysense.blogspot.com/2010/05/virtualbox-using-hyper-v-vhd-image.html">how to open a Hyper-V VM in VirtualBox</a>.&nbsp; </p> <p><a href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML572dd9e.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-right-width: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-left-width: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="SNAGHTML572dd9e" border="0" alt="SNAGHTML572dd9e" src="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/SNAGHTML572dd9e_thumb.png" width="565" height="422"></a></p> <p>You are done.&nbsp; Launch your ALM virtual machine and “get your learning on!”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organizing Your TFS Build Definitions with Inmeta Build Explorer]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/10/07/organizing-your-tfs-build-definitions-with-inmeta-build-explorer/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/10/07/organizing-your-tfs-build-definitions-with-inmeta-build-explorer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The project I am currently working on is using Team Foundation Server for builds and we have a lot of build definitions.  The project is a large enterprise-level project, with multiple Visual Studio solutions.  Each Visual Studio solution has at least two branches – maybe more – and usually a corresponding build definition for most of those branches.  Hopefully that gives you a good idea of the number of build definitions.</p>

<p>One of my coworkers at this client was nice enough to point me towards the Inmeta Build Explorer add-in for Visual Studio.  The add-in plugs directly into the Team Explorer window in Visual Studio and provides you an organized hierarchical list of the build definitions in your team project.  This is done using a naming convention for the builds in your team project.  The add-in uses “.” as the default separator, but the developers of the add-in were nice enough to make it customizable.  And the Inmeta Build Explorer add-in is a client plugin, so only the developers on your team that are interested in using it have to install it – if you don’t look at the build definitions on a daily basis, then you don’t have to install it.</p>

<p>Just to give you an idea of the structure of the builds underneath the Inmeta Build Explorer node, here is what the Inmeta Build Explorer add-in looks like in our team project.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/Win7Dev-1-1-2.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-214 aligncenter" title="Win7Dev-1-1-2" src="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/Win7Dev-1-1-2.jpg" alt="" width="318" height="342" /></a></p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>Another nice feature of this add-in is the ability to easily queue up the “default” build for a specific build definition.  If you right-click on one of the builds, an option named “Queue Default Build(s)” is available on the context menu.  Selecting this will automatically queue a new build for that build definition, bypassing the build properties window that lets you override the default build settings.</p>

<p>You can get the Inmeta Build Explorer on the Visual Studio Gallery.</p>

<p><a title="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/35daa606-4917-43c4-98ab-38632d9dbd45" href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/35daa606-4917-43c4-98ab-38632d9dbd45">http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/35daa606-4917-43c4-98ab-38632d9dbd45</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Webinar: Continuous Deployment with Team Build and MSDeploy]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/04/27/webinar-continuous-deployment-with-team-build-and-msdeploy/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/04/27/webinar-continuous-deployment-with-team-build-and-msdeploy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Caffeine, pizza, and anxiety are regular tools for a production deployment.  Watch and learn how Team Foundation Build 2010 and MSDeploy can turn the last hurdle of software development into a moment of zen.  Deploying software can be hard, but it doesn’t have to be if you practice the hard things along the way.</p>

<p>In this webinar, we’ll take a look at how to configure a new <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms181710(VS.80).aspx" target="_blank">Team Build</a> definition for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration" target="_blank">Continuous Integration</a>.  Then we will walk through creating an MSDeploy package from an ASP.NET MVC project, and automate the execution of the MSDeploy package to remote servers using our Continuous Integration build definition.</p>

<p>The webinar will be April 28th from 12pm-1pm EST.  For more information and to register to attend, check out the <a href="http://www.sds-consulting.com/tfs-training-series-free-continuous-deployment-team-build-and-msdeploy" target="_blank">Strategic Data Systems website</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/smemon/4974327595/in/photostream/"><img class="size-full wp-image-223 " title="Integration" src="http://derekhubbard.github.io/images/posts/4974327595_c1d790df86_o.png" alt="" width="750" height="250" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heterogeneous Development with Team Foundation and Visual Studio 2010]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/04/02/heterogeneous-development-with-team-foundation-and-visual-studio-2010/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/04/02/heterogeneous-development-with-team-foundation-and-visual-studio-2010</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are doing any sort of development in a heterogeneous development environment (say with Microsoft .NET and/or Java, Python, Ruby, etc.) and are interested in how you can leverage a single product that can provide a single source control repository as well as a single place for developers to manage their development process, then you may be interested in an upcoming webinar I will be giving on “Heterogeneous Development with Team Foundation and Visual Studio 2010”.&#160; </p>  <p>In this webinar, we’ll take a look at how to use <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/visualstudio/en-us/products/2010-editions/team-explorer-everywhere" target="_blank">Team Explorer Everywhere</a>, which is included with <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/visualstudio/en-us/products/2010-editions/team-foundation-server" target="_blank">Team Foundation Server 2010</a>.&#160; Team Explorer Everywhere can be integrated into any <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eclipse_(software)" target="_blank">Eclipse-based</a> development environment.&#160; Once integrated, users will be able to interact with Team Foundation Server directly from within their Eclipse-based development environment and use Team Foundation Server for both version control and process management.&#160; </p>  <p>The webinar will be April 7th from 12pm-1pm EST.&#160; For more information and to register to attend, check out the <a href="http://www.sds-consulting.com/tfs-training-series-free-heterogeneous-development-team-foundation-and-visual-studio-2010" target="_blank">Strategic Data Systems website</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Rework]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/04/02/book-review-rework/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/04/02/book-review-rework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Rework-Jason-Fried/dp/0307463745/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1301795502&amp;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><em>Rework</em></a> by Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson. Pub by Crown Publishing. ISBN 10 9780307463746.</p>

<p>So I know that this book has been out for awhile, and actually, I have owned this book for awhile.  Actually, if we’re being exact, I’ve owned two copies of this book for quite some time now.  It’s a funny story… ok, so not actually, but anyway – here is why I have two copies of this book.  I ordered the book off <a href="http://www.amazon.com/" target="_blank">Amazon.com</a> when it first hit bookshelves.  However, I wanted to read it so badly and I couldn’t wait until it was shipped to my house, so I picked up a copy at the local <a href="http://www.booksandco.com/" target="_blank">Books and Company</a> store.  I took that copy home, and started to read it.  And, eventually, the copy I had ordered off Amazon.com finally arrived.  Although at that point, life had already moved on and I never did remember to take back the original copy I had picked up at Books and Company.  So, now I have two copies.  And I finally finished reading one of those copies just a couple weeks ago on the plane, and here is the review.  This blog post does have a point – I promise.</p>

<p><em>Rework</em> is one of the most interesting – and most realistic – business books I have seen in a while.  And it’s one of the more unique business books I have read.  It’s unique because, in all of its simplicity, the authors of this book seem to understand how to start (and run) a business more than most others.</p>

<p>The authors start off with some very basic suggestions on how to start your own business.  But rather than walk you through the step-by-step process for creating everything from business cards to marketing material, they help the reader consider the most important things first.  You don’t have to give up your 9-5 job to start doing something you love.  You can start working on something with a little as an hour a day, and if you’re truly passionate about this interest and it’s more than a hobby, then you will stick with it – oh, and about those business cards – they can wait.  The key is to prioritize your list of tasks and expenses, and focus on the most important things first.</p>

<p>The book continues by discussing how to build your idea into a productive business, when to grow (or not grow) your business, and how to deal with everyday business scenarios like hiring, marketing, and bad press.</p>

<p>If you’re looking for a no-crap book on how to turn your ideas into a sustainable business, then look no further – start by reading <em>Rework</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Dayton IIBA Chapter Meeting]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/03/09/speaking-at-dayton-iiba-chapter-meeting-2/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2011/03/09/speaking-at-dayton-iiba-chapter-meeting-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I know this is late notice, but I will be speaking at the next Dayton International Institute of Business Analysis (IIBA) chapter meeting, which is tonight – March 9th!</p>  <p>In this presentation, we’ll start with a brief introduction of what it means to be agile, and then we’ll talk about how business analysts fit into an agile project team and how to work effectively with the rest of the project team to help your next project succeed.&#160; </p>  <p>For information on the event, check out the <a href="http://dayton.theiiba.org/index.php/home">Dayton IIBA chapter website</a> or the <a href="http://dayton.theiiba.org/index.php/chapter-events/event-listing/details/21-Mar%202011">event page for tonight’s chapter meeting</a>!&#160; If you would like to attend, you can rsvp via email to <a href="mailto:dayton.iiba@gmail.com">dayton.iiba@gmail.com</a>.&#160; </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog 2.0: New Engine, New Template, New Posts]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2010/03/20/blog-2-0-new-engine-new-template-new-posts/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2010/03/20/blog-2-0-new-engine-new-template-new-posts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have made a significant number of changes to this blog over the last month or so.  Here are the details…</p>

<h3>New Blog Engine - WordPress</h3>

<p>I made the switch to <a href="http://wordpress.com/" target="_blank">WordPress</a>.  My blog was originally hosted with <a href="http://www.blogger.com" target="_blank">Blogger</a>, but in the beginning of February, I received an email from <a href="http://www.google.com" target="_blank">Google</a> stating that only 0.5% of the active blogs published using Blogger were using the <a href="http://www.google.com/support/blogger/bin/topic.py?hl=en&amp;topic=12460" target="_blank">FTP publishing option</a> and they are <a href="http://blogger-ftp.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">no longer going to support this feature</a>.  I really liked the FTP publishing option that was available to Blogger users because it allowed me to host my blog “inside” a typical <a href="http://www.asp.net/" target="_blank">ASP.NET</a> site, complete with <a href="http://jquery.com/" target="_blank">jQuery</a> and even <a href="http://www.silverlight.net/" target="_blank">Silverlight</a> and/or <a href="http://www.adobe.com/flashplatform/" target="_blank">Flash</a> content.  Unfortunately, this publishing option is no longer supported after March 26th, so WordPress is my new home.</p>

<h3>New Blog Template – Extremely Simple</h3>

<p>I also decided to switch up the blog template during the transition from Blogger to WordPress.  The original blog template was pretty simple and this one is even simpler.  This blog is about the content and not the theme, so keeping the theme simple is important to me.</p>

<h3>New Posts – Coming Soon</h3>

<p>Finally, new posts are on their way.  I have about 3 new posts in progress now, mostly technical focused posts as of right now, with the exception of one post on developer soft skills.  Look for these coming soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impact Analysis in SQL Server 2008]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/11/03/impact-analysis-in-sql-server-2008/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/11/03/impact-analysis-in-sql-server-2008</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A colleague of mine and I were confronted with an issue today when we did not perform a proper code search before making some database schema changes to an existing SQL Server 2008 database.&#160; This made me realize that I don&#8217;t think I&#8217;ve ever performed an impact analysis on code within SQL Server.&#160; Impact analysis on my application code is like second nature to me, but the idea of analyzing my SQL Server code was not something I had thought of before.</p>  <p>Impact analysis is extremely important when making changes to an existing application - especially if the changes you are making include database schema changes.&#160; This is even more important if the application you are changing is an existing production application. if users are working with your application, they aren&#8217;t going to be happy if they have runtime errors in their application every time you touch the codebase.&#160; The specific project my colleague and I are working on is still in development, so we didn&#8217;t cause any major production issues as a result of the schema changes we made, however, this may not be the case every time we make schema changes in the future.</p>  <p>A quick search on <a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com">StackOverflow</a> shows that I&#8217;m not the first developer to ask this <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1364633/search-for-a-key-word-in-all-the-stored-procs-for-a-given-db">question</a>.&#160; Also, I&#8217;m sure I&#8217;m not the last person to ask about it either, so I thought it was worth repeating here in case anyone else is interested.</p>  <p>In my scenario, I needed a way to search all of the existing stored procedures to see if an existing database column and relationship were referenced.&#160; The easiest way to do this is a quick keyword search through all of the stored procedures.&#160; Our database has over 100 stored procedures, so searching each one by hand wasn&#8217;t feasible.&#160; Plus, we&#8217;re developers - when we are confronted with situations like this in the future, we should be looking for a quick way to automate this type of task.</p>  <p>One of the responses to this <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1364633/search-for-a-key-word-in-all-the-stored-procs-for-a-given-db">question on StackOverflow</a> suggest running a quick SQL query against the database you want to search, plugging in the keyword you want to search for.</p>  <pre>SELECT DISTINCT(sysobjects.name)<br />FROM sysobjects,syscomments
WHERE sysobjects.id = syscomments.id
AND sysobjects.type = 'P'
AND sysobjects.category=0
AND CHARINDEX(&lt;the keyword&gt;,syscomments.text)&gt;0</pre>

<p>Just replace the placeholder &#8216;&lt;the keyword&gt;&#8217; with the keyword you want to find.&#160; This query can easily be thrown into a stored procedure (with the keyword as a parameter) and you can call this every time you need to perform an impact analysis on your SQL Server stored procedures before making changes in the future.&#160; Your colleagues. and your boss. will appreciate this, trust me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upcoming Speaking Event]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/10/29/upcoming-speaking-event/"/>
    <updated>2009-10-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/10/29/upcoming-speaking-event</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will be speaking at the upcoming University of Dayton School of Engineering Career Day.  This event is open to high school students, parents, guidance counselors, and teachers that are interested in learning more about engineering disciplines and the University of Dayton School of Engineering.  After presentations by engineers in each of the major engineering fields, students are treated to lunch and tours of the schools engineering labs (which have just been recently updated, so I&#8217;m excited to go back and see them).</p>

<p>I&#8217;m honored to be asked back as a speaker at this event (I&#8217;ve spoken at this event several times in the past) and look forward to sharing my experiences as a computer engineer.  Hopefully I&#8217;ll be able to generate some interest in the exciting opportunities that are available in our field!</p>

<p>For more info on the event, check out the info page <a href="http://www.udayton.edu/engineering/hs_programs/career_awareness_day.php">here</a>.  Unfortunately registration is full, but you can add your name to a wait list if you are interested in attending.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code and Coffee]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/09/17/code-and-coffee/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/09/17/code-and-coffee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a developer, I think it&#8217;s really important to stay involved in the community.&#160; Attending local user groups, code camps, and conferences are a great way to connect and stay involved with other developers in your community - this is on top of the great content presented in the sessions at these events.&#160; These community venues are great, but a lot of times they only occur on a limited basis in our local areas - once a month for user groups unless you live in an area with additional user groups in a neighboring city and, in the case of most code camps<a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_OEUY07e5x-k/SrKLbBxPorI/AAAAAAAAAEY/M-DJxUf5OPM/s1600-h/coffeebeans3.jpg"><img border="0" alt="coffeebeans" align="right" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_OEUY07e5x-k/SrKLbwholrI/AAAAAAAAAEc/t9bWUeS6prw/coffeebeans_thumb1.jpg?imgmax=800" width="244" height="164" /></a> and conferences, maybe once per year.</p>  <p>Code and Coffee is a great way to keep community going on a more frequent basis.&#160; This is typically an informal meet up on a scheduled basis - usually once a week - at a coffee shop in your neighborhood.&#160; Just about every coffee shop has large group tables, free wifi, and caffeine and you would be amazed at how much you can learn just by doing an hour or two of pair programming with other developers in your area.&#160; </p>  <p>The Dayton, Ohio Code and Coffee meet up is on Tuesday mornings at <a href="http://www.bing.com/maps/default.aspx?v=2&amp;FORM=LMLTCC&amp;cp=39.694286~-84.10151&amp;style=r&amp;lvl=16&amp;tilt=-90&amp;dir=0&amp;alt=-1000&amp;phx=0&amp;phy=0&amp;phscl=1&amp;ss=yp.caribou%20coffee~pg.1~sst.0&amp;encType=1">Caribou Coffee at The Greene</a>.&#160; We typically start at 715am and finish up whenever the last person needs to leave.&#160; In the last several months, we have worked through <a href="http://github.com/edgecase/ruby_koans">EdgeCase&#8217;s Ruby Koans</a> and <a href="http://github.com/schambers/solid-principles">Sean Chambers&#8217; SOLID presentation</a> as a group.&#160; The schedule is really informal (you can read that as &quot;there is no schedule&quot;), so who knows what is next. </p>  <p>If there is a meet up similar to this in your area already, I encourage you to get involved.&#160; Here are the groups I know of in the southwest Ohio area:</p>  <ul>   <li>Cincinnati - <a href="http://cinnug.org/">Bitslingers</a>, Monday evenings at <a href="http://www.bing.com/maps/?v=2&amp;ss=ypid.YN691x12091955&amp;encType=1">Panera Bread at Deerfield Towne Center</a> (6pm) and Thursday mornings Panera Bread in Kenwood (630am) </li>    <li>Columbus - <a href="http://www.codeandcoffee.info/">Code and Coffee</a>, Friday mornings at varied locations </li>    <li>Dayton - Code and Coffee, Tuesday mornings at <a href="http://www.bing.com/maps/default.aspx?v=2&amp;FORM=LMLTCC&amp;cp=39.694286~-84.10151&amp;style=r&amp;lvl=16&amp;tilt=-90&amp;dir=0&amp;alt=-1000&amp;phx=0&amp;phy=0&amp;phscl=1&amp;ss=yp.caribou%20coffee~pg.1~sst.0&amp;encType=1">Caribou Coffee at The Greene</a>, 715am</li> </ul>  <p>If there isn&#8217;t a Code and Coffee group in your area, maybe there is a similar group of developers that meet for lunch or in the evening.&#160; If you still can&#8217;t find one, why not start your own?&#160; These sessions are usually very informal, but one of the key things I would suggest is to keep it as open as possible.&#160; In other words, don&#8217;t exclude people by making it a language specific group.&#160; All developers, regardless of language preference, should be invited to attend and get involved.&#160; We can learn a lot from each other by reaching across the language and technology boundaries. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[User Experiences and Empathy]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/07/23/user-experiences-and-empathy/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/07/23/user-experiences-and-empathy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been reading a lot lately, mostly around how to develop better user experiences. Most of my recent reads have been less focused on programming languages and more focused on strategies and thought processes that empower developers to build better user experiences.</p>

<p>The bottom line is, the user experience is arguably the most important aspect of any project. Sure, it is important to have a functioning application that works as expected, but if the user experience does not let your users use the application functionality to solve their problems and meet their needs, the extra features you added to the application code are worthless. This does not mean that the user experience of every application needs to be built in some form of rich application environment (i.e. Silverlight, WPF, Flex, etc.). Even though this would certainly be nice eye candy, some applications just do not warrant the need for a rich application interface. But that does not mean the user experience is not important – you can develop a great user experience regardless of the UI technology.</p>

<p>One of the books I am currently reading is “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Subject-Change-Creating-Products-Uncertain/dp/0596516835/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1245298381&amp;sr=8-1">Subject to Change: Creating Great Products and Services for an Uncertain World</a>” by a group of authors from <a href="http://adaptivepath.com/">Adaptive Path</a>, a user experience strategy and design company located in San Francisco. Here are a few excellent points I have picked up on so far that I thought were worth sharing.</p>

<h3>Empathy is your most valuable tool</h3>

<p>A key point that is stressed throughout the book is the use of empathy in user experience design. To quote the folks from Adaptive Path, “empathy is an understanding of a person or group’s subjective experience by sharing that experience vicariously.” If you have empathy for your audience, you can really start to see what drives their behaviors rather than just observing them as some type of action.</p>

<h3>Empathy is not sympathy</h3>

<p>Empathy and sympathy are two completely different emotions. Sympathy could be (1) pity for the user or it could be (2) a feeling generated by actually sharing an experience with the user, both of which do not have a place in the software design process. Pity can sometimes lead to a sense of superiority, which is definitely not what you want. And If the user and the designer both share the same experience, the designer’s objectivity can be removed and he/she can sometimes get “too close” to the problem. Empathy however keeps you at a distance with an objective point of view.</p>

<h3>Users are human beings and not market segments</h3>

<p>Having empathy for your users and understanding them as human beings and not as market segments or demographics will greatly increase your chances of developing a quality user experience. One example of developing empathy, which is mentioned in the book, is the redesign of two Huggies products by Kimberly-Clark. After conducting a significant amount of research in families homes, they noticed that parents were often struggling to hold babies while diapering and bathing them. Based on these observations, the product designers at Kimberly-Clark redesigned their baby wipes packaging to make it easier to pull out wipes with one hand. By observing users in their homes while they live their everyday lives, researchers were able to develop empathy for the users (in this case, the parents) in regards to how they use the product.</p>

<p>So the key points are (1) empathy, not sympathy, and (2) human beings, not market segments. Once you understand these points, you are well on your way to better understanding your users and their needs.</p>

<p>Anything else you think is key when it comes to empathy and user experiences? Feel free to share your thoughts in the comments.</p>

<p>This work is licensed under a <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons license.</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Blog Template]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/06/07/new-blog-template/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/06/07/new-blog-template</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m in the process of updating my blog template, so if you happen to stumble on this blog and wonder why the styles keep changing, well now you know why.</p>

<p>The blog is hosted by Blogger (I know, I know… but I think Blogger is great as far as the engine goes).  The actual interfaces you use to manage templates, styles, posts, etc. are somewhat limited at best, but there are ways to work smarter when it comes to this stuff… more on that later.</p>

<p>So far, the theme is simple, which is what I’m looking for, but I think it needs something else so expect more changes to come in the near future. I’m looking at adding some Silverlight controls and/or navigation as well as some Twitter info.</p>

<p>Oh yeah, you can also expect some content in the near future as well. I have a couple things in the pipeline, so – stay tuned!</p>

<p>This work is licensed under a <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons license.</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Beginning]]></title>
    <link href="http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/02/03/the-beginning/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://derekhubbard.github.io/blog/2009/02/03/the-beginning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s true&#8230; I&#8217;m finally starting a blog. I have actually been thinking of starting a blog for awhile now, but it has taken a considerable amount of thought to decide what I would actually want to blog about.</p>

<p>I knew whatever I blogged about, it would be software related. That was the easy decision. But what software? Should this blog be about one specific language (C#, Java, etc.) or should I branch out and include other languages? Do I just blog about features of the language I&#8217;m familiar with, or do I also blog about features I&#8217;m learning? Or maybe I should just blog about IDE&#8217;s and utilities that make software development easier (<a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/default.aspx">Visual Studio</a>, <a href="http://www.linqpad.net/">LINQPad</a>, <a href="http://www.flos-freeware.ch/notepad2.html">Notepad2</a>&#8230;).</p>

<p>A little background info on me, to give you an idea where I&#8217;m coming from. I graduated from the <a href="http://www.udayton.edu/">University of Dayton</a> in 2004 with a bachelors degree in Computer Engineering. My first job out of college was with a consulting company in Cincinnati called Software Architects (SARK for short). I spent three years with this company as a Java/Oracle developer. They aren&#8217;t around anymore as they were purchased by <a href="http://www.us.sogeti.com/">Sogeti USA LLC</a> shortly before I left.</p>

<p>In June 2007, my wife and I moved to Dayton, Ohio for her job. I also switched jobs at that point and accepted a .NET developer position with <a href="http://www.theberrycompany.com/">The Berry Company</a>. Switching from Java to .NET was a farily easy transition for me - for the most part, the languages are fairly similar. Now I&#8217;m a Senior Web Developer with Berry and have been there for the last 1.5+ years.</p>

<p>Even though I&#8217;m a .NET web developer mostly developing in ASP.NET, I&#8217;m extremely interested in other software development technologies. For example, I would really like to learn more about development on a Mac (<a href="http://developer.apple.com/cocoa/">Cocoa</a> and Objective C). I am also interested in learning more about the <a href="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/">Google Web Toolkit</a> (GWT) and the <a href="http://developer.yahoo.com/yui/">Yahoo User Interface</a> (YUI) libraries.</p>

<p>So getting back to what the topic of this blog is going to be. After a lot of consideration about what I know, what I enjoy doing, and what else I would like to learn, I am hoping this blog will be about everything I mentioned before. I would like to share what I can, both from my experiences at work as I develop in ASP.NET and C#, but also from my experiences outside of work as I learn and play around with new technologies.</p>

<p>As I come across new programming problems and solutions at work, I will be sure to blog about them here as it is very probable there is someone else in the world that is trying to solve the same problem as me at the exact same time. Also, I hope to blog about new technologies as I learn them - sharing and documenting my learning experiences (both the good ones and the mistakes).</p>

<p>Hopefully this blog will be of interest to you and a learning experience for all of us. If you have any feedback, feel free to post any comments or suggestions and I will do my best to respond to each one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
